Guide to the Mount Vernon Seminary and College Office of the President records, 1929-1989 MVC0036.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary and College Office of the President records
1929-1989
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MVC0036.RG
3.5 Linear Feet 7 document boxes
The Mount Vernon Seminary was officially established by Elizabeth Somers in 1875 and a two year junior college was added in 1927. The Junior College remained open until 1969, when Mount Vernon College became a four-year unversity. The university was an independent institution until 1999, when it became affilated with The George Washington University. This collection includes files from the Office of the President that cover a range of topics, including but not limited to commencement, development, enrollment, inagurations, and finances. The materials date from 1929-1989.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Mount Vernon Seminary and College archives were acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. The collection was transferred to the Foggy Bottom campus in 2009.
Arrangement
Arranged into 2 series: Administrative files and Photographs.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains administrative files and files from the Office of the President at Mount Vernon Seminary, Junior College, and College. The materials date from 1929-1989. It is likely this collection will continue to grow as more records are transferred and uncovered.
Biographical / Historical
Mount Vernon Seminary, later Mount Vernon College, had eight presidents from its founding in 1875 to 1999, when it was acquired by George Washington University. The eight presidents were: Elizabeth Somers, Adelia Gates Hensley, Jean Dean Cole, George W. Lloyd, Peter Pelham, Victoria Schuck, Jane Evans, and LucyAnn Geiselman.
The Mount Vernon Seminary began in 1875 as a private high school and junior college for women, founded by Elizabeth J. Somers. The George Washington University initially affiliated with Mount Vernon College, and ultimately acquired the college's property and legacy in 1999.
The first school of higher education available to women in Washington, D.C., Mount Vernon Seminary and College had five different locations throughout its history:
1875-1880: Elizabeth Somers began tutoring the young daughters of prominent Washington men in her home at 204 F Street, NW in Washington, DC.
1880-1917: The school moved to 1100 M Street, NW where it expanded rapidly to include three additional houses, a courtyard, tennis court, and basketball court.
1917-1942: Having outgrown its M Street location, the school moved to a 15-acre campus on Nebraska Avenue, NW. In 1942, the United States Navy took over the Nebraska Avenue campus to use its facilities for the war effort.
1943-1946: The school resumed courses in February 1943 at the top floor of a Garfinckel's department store building in the Spring Valley neighborhood of Washington, D.C.
1946-1999: Between 1944 and 1946, the school built a new 21-acre campus located on Foxhall Road in Washington, D.C. using money granted to the college by the United States Navy in compensation for the military takeover of its property.
The last Seminary class graduated in 1969, and the school was then officially renamed to Mount Vernon Junior College. In 1976, Mount Vernon College became an accredited four year college. In 1997, the Board of Trustees decided that the College would close as an independent institution. As of June 30, 1999, Mount Vernon became affiliated with The George Washington University.
Women -- Education; Women's colleges; Mount Vernon Seminary; Mount Vernon College
- Administrative files, 1929-1989; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains administrative files from the Office of the President of Mount Vernon Seminary, Junior College, and College including materials concerning commencement, inagurations, development, finances, enrollement, etc. The materials in this series date from 1929-1989.
  - Acceptances - 75th anniversary, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Accreditation report on outcomes, 1962; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alumnae Council, 1961-1967; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American University in Rome, 1976-1977; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - B.A. program congratulatory letters, 1973; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board reports, 1941-1942; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bulletin, 1970-1971; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chapel, 1968-1970; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Charge to graduating class, 1977; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Commencement, 1969-1977; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Commencement, 1979; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Commencements and convocations, 1970-1973; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Convocation, 1966; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Convocation, 1975-1979; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1950; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cum Laude Society, circa 1960-1969; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Dean's office, 1967; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Dedication of Florence Hollis Hand chapel, 1970; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Development committee, 1974-1975; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Development committee meeting March 30th, 1977; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Development office, 1970-1980; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Devlopment ideas, 1978-1981; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Dedication of site and cornerstone ceremony, 1945-1946; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Discovery Inc., 1973-1976; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Dr. Eileen P. Kuhns, 1967; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Eleanor Lansing Dulles autobriography chapter, 1979; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Endowment, 1941; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Enrollment charts, 1959-1964; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Enrollment statistics, 1929-1953; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Executive committee, 1969-1972; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Faculty handbook cover, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Faculty teaching load, 1962-1967; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Fathers' Association steering committee: constitution and by-laws, 1958; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Fathers' Day, 1958-1959; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Fathers' Club meetings, 1960-1968; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Fathers' Club of Mt. Vernon treasurer's reports, financial statements, dues, etc., 1959-1963; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Field house - history, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Finance/executive committee meeting minutes, 1977-1978; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Floor plans, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Flora Bridges Harper, 1967; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Founders' Day: sale lecture, 1961-1977; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Front Page, 1974-1975; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Headmistress' responsibilities, 1960; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Honorary degree, 1979; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Hood College recruitment plan, 1972-1974; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Inagural greetings, 1978; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Invitations to Evans' inaguration, 1978; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Jane Evans' inagural invitations, 1981; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Jean Dean Cole fund, 1950; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Judge Whaley, 1938-1943; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Library, 1958-1970; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Letters/press clips, circa 1920; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Long rangle planning committee, 1988-1989; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Merrilyn Bordes Quinn files, 1979-1981; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous clippings and correspondence, circa 1930-1960; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Miscellanous loose files, undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Miss Ames, 1958-1959; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Miss Coles' memoriam, undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Mount Vernon College Board of Directors, 1970; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Mount Vernon College inaguration, 1981; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Mount Vernon Seminary building program report to Mr. Preston, 1947; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Mount Vernon Seminary long range planning report, 1964; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Mount Vernon Seminary and Junior College history, 1967; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Mrs. Herbert L. Willet, Jr. (nee Clara Hoskins), undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - MVC information, circa 1970; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - National Junior Honor Society certificates, undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Optima (Order of the Lily), 1963-1964; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - One hundredth anniversary general, 1974-1975; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Parents' council, 1961-1967; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Peter Pelham installation, 89th Founders' Day, 1962-1963; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Phasing out of Mount Vernon Seminary, 1965; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Philosophy of the school, 1958; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Planning committee reports, 1964; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Post Script, 1972-1974; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Potomac Current - press coverage, 1972-1973; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - PR - Bobbie Kilberg, 1972-1973; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Press coverage, 1977-1978; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Press coverage Architectural Awards - Hartman-Cox, 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Property (school), 1960; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Reprints - press coverage, 1971; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Ringing ceremony, 1964; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Scholarships - Hawley; Eugene & Agnes Meyer, 1940-1968; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Schuck inaguration, 1978; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Second class postage permit, 1972-1978; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Seminary closing, undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Staff - length of service and Christmas fund, 1940-1961; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Study abroad program, 1972-1974; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Study abroad promotion, 1972-1975; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Task force - B.A. program, 1973; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Title III and IV, 1978-1981; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Trips - United Nations, Lake Placid, 1954-1962; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Tuition scale, 1962; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Valerie Walton memorial, 1977; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Weis scholarship fund, 1979; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Photographs, circa 1960-1980; Series 2
  This series contains photographs from the Office of the President at Mount Vernon College. They include photographs of students studying, interning, at leisure, photos of convocation, the Board of Trustees, etc. The materials in this series date from circa 1960-1980.
  - Academic interns, circa 1965-1975; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Board of Trustees, circa 1960-1980; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Board of Trustees, circa 1960-1979; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Childhood education, circa 1965-1975; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Convocation, 1967; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous photos and negatives, circa 1960-1980; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1970s photos, circa 1970-1979; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous 1970s photos, circa 1970-1979; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous 1970s photos, circa 1970-1979; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous photos, undated; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Mrs. Post photos, undated; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Public affairs, circa 1960-1980; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Students leisure, circa 1960-1980; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Students walking photos, circa 1970-1979; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Students studying, circa 1970-1979; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Study abroad, circa 1970-1979; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Study abroad, circa 1970-1979; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 14)